A Finding Aid to the Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman Papers, circa 1930s-2006, bulk 1942-2005, in the Archives of American Art AAA.koppchai
Archives of American Art
Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman papers
bulk 1942-2005
circa 1930s-2006
AAA.koppchai
Archives of American Art
4 Linear feet
The papers of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman measure 4.0 linear feet and date from circa 1930s-2006, bulk 1942-2005. The collection documents the activities of Chaim Koppelman and his wife, Dorothy as artists and educators, and to a lesser extent their affiliation with the Terrain Gallery. Materials include biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, subject files, teaching files, exhibition files, personal business records, scrapbooks, printed material, sketches, sketchbooks, and photographs.
Chaim Koppelman
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman in 2006.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art also holds the Terrain Gallery records of which Dorothy Koppelman is the director.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Chaim Koppelman (1920-2009) lived and worked in New York as a printmaker and educator. Painter and educator Dorothy Koppelman (1920-) resides and works in New York City.
Chaim Koppelman was born in Brooklyn in 1920. Koppelman studied at the American Artists School with Carl Holty and at the Art Students League with Jose De Creeft and Will Barnet. In 1942, Koppelman was drafted in the U.S. Army. Before going overseas in 1943, he married Dorothy Meyers. In the army, Koppelman continued his studies in painting and sculpture, where he attended the Art College in Western England, Bristol and the Beaux Arts School in Reims, France. Chaim Koppelman took part in the Normandy invasion and was awarded the Bronze Star for his service.
After Koppelman returned to New York in 1944, he studied at the Amédée Ozenfant School, where he eventually became Ozenfant's assistant. Around this time, Koppelman turned from painting and sculpture to printmaking. In 1955, Chaim Koppelman, his wife, Dorothy, and other students of Eli Siegel's School of Aesthetic Realism established the Terrain Gallery. For many years, Koppelman was the head of the gallery's Print Division and then later appointed the gallery's advisory director.
Chaim Koppelman held a number of teaching positions in universities and arts institutions. He lectured at Brooklyn College, the Art Education Department from 1950-1960. In 1959, Koppelman founded the Printmaking Division at the School of Visual Arts, where he served on the school's faculty until 2007. At the Aesthetic Realism Foundation, he trained artists how to incorporate their artwork in their everyday lives.
Among the awards Chaim Koppelman received were: two Tiffany Grants, 1956, 1959; New York Artists Equity Annual Awards Honoring Will Barnet, Robert Blackburn, Chaim Koppelman, 1992; and the Purchase Prize, Art Students League in 2005. Koppelman was a member of the National Academy of Design and a member of the Society of American Graphic Artists (SAGA). In 2004, SAGA presented him with the Lifetime Achievement Award.
In addition to his many solo and group exhibitions at the Terrain Gallery, Chaim Koppelman's work was featured at the Beatrice Conde Gallery, International Print Center (New York), Library of Congress, and Minneapolis Institute of Arts. His prints are in the collections of the Guggenheim Museum, Museum of Modern Art (New York), Metropolitan Museum of Art, Victoria and Albert Museum in London, and the National Gallery.
In December 2009, Koppelman died at age 89 in New York City.
Born in 1920, Dorothy Koppelman graduated from Brooklyn College. She attended the Art Students League and American Artists School, where she trained under Joseph Solman. During this time, Dorothy studied with Eli Siegel, the founder of Aesthetic Realism.
Dorothy Koppelman has had a number of solo and group exhibitions at the Terrain Gallery. She has also shown her paintings at the Atlantic Gallery, Art Gallery of Binghamton, New York, Beatrice Conde Gallery, Brooklyn Art Museum, and the Whitney Biennial 2006 Peace Tower.
Dorothy Koppelman has served on the faculty at several arts institutions: National Academy of Design, New York Artists Equity Association, and the School of Visual Arts. She has given presentations on Aesthetic Realism at the Fondazione Piero della Francesa in Italy and at the 31st World Congress of the International Society for Education.
She is a member of several professional organizations including the American Society of Contemporary Artists and New York Artists Equity. She has received a Honorable Mention from the Brooklyn Society of Artists, 1957; a Tiffany Grant for painting, 1965; and awards from the American Society of Contemporary Artists, 1996, 1999. Dorothy's work has been included in the collections of Hampton University, West Virginia; Rosenzweig Museum, Durham, North Carolina; New-York Historical Society; Yale University, as well as other institutions.
Dorothy Koppelman lives in New York City. She serves as a consultant on the faculty of the Aesthetic Realism Foundation.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman measure 4.0 linear feet and date from circa 1930s-2006, bulk 1942-2005. The collection documents the activities of Chaim Koppelman and his wife, Dorothy as artists and educators, and to a lesser extent their affiliation with the Terrain Gallery. Materials include biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, subject files, teaching files, exhibition files, personal business records, scrapbooks, printed material, sketches, sketchbooks, and photographs.
Scattered biographical material includes resumes, an artist's statement, copies of entries in Who Is Who directories, and miscellaneous items.
Correspondence includes personal correspondence and general correspondence. Personal correspondence mostly consists of Chaim Koppelman's letters written to Dorothy while he was serving in the U.S. Army during World War II. He describes his daily activities, observations on army life, and his travels while stationed in England, France, and Germany. Of interest is Chaim Koppelman's letter to Dorothy describing his meeting Picasso and visiting the artist's studio. Personal correspondence also contains Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman's letters with family and friends. Notable correspondents include Sari Dienes, Nat Herz, Sheldon Kranz, Amédée Ozenfant, Hilla Rebay, and Theodoros Stamos. Hilla Rebay's letters to Chaim Koppelman discuss museum-related activities at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation, including the Guggenheim's memorial exhibition for Wassily Kandinsky. There is also a file of letters from Eli Siegel to Chaim Koppelman.
General correspondence includes mostly incoming letters to Chaim Koppelman from collectors, colleagues, students, and arts institutions. Frequent correspondents include: Associated American Artists, American Federation of the Arts, Audubon Artists, DeCordova and Dana Museum and Park, Pratt Graphics Center and Print Council of America.
Writings and notes contain annotated typescripts and handwritten drafts by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman. Chaim Koppelman's writings include essays on art, artists, and printmaking; also found are some poems. Dorothy Koppelman's writings consist of artist's statements and essay-length pieces that were prepared for talks held at the Terrain Gallery and other venues. Also found is a sound recording of Chaim Koppelman's 1968 conversation with Richard Anuszkiewicz, Roy Lichtenstein, and Clayton Pond; the artists discuss the influence of Eli Siegel's Theory of Opposites on their work.
Subject files document the activities, projects, and professional affiliations of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman. Included are materials on exhibitions, applications for fellowships and grants, awards, drafts of writings, donations and acquisitions of artwork by museums. Teaching files provide an overview of the faculty positions held by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman over the course of their careers. Found are extensive files on Chaim Koppelman's tenure at the School of Visual Arts. Exhibition files chronicle the Koppelmans' solo and group shows at the Terrain and other venues; substantive files contain Chaim Koppelman's correspondence with museums and arts institutions and sales information.
Two scrapbooks consist of exhibition-related materials: artist's statements, press releases, awards, printed material, and photographs of artwork. Artwork includes sketches and illustrated letters by Chaim Koppelman. Also included are twenty annotated sketchbooks by Chaim Koppelman and a sketchbook by Dorothy Koppelman.
Photographs and snapshots are of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman; many of the snapshots of Chaim Koppelman and others document his army service while stationed in the United States and Europe. Four photograph albums include black and white photographs of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman in their studio; included are snapshots of the Koppelmans' with family and friends at exhibition openings, gatherings, and on their travels. There are photographs of Regina Dienes, Gerson Lieber, Bernard Olshan, Joseph Solman, and Theodoros Stamos.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 12 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1940-2001 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1942-2003 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1930s-1989, 2005 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1942-2004 (Boxes 1-2; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Teaching Files, 1940s-2006 (Box 2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Exhibition Files, 1940s-2005 (Boxes 2-3; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Personal Business Records, 1944-1969 (Box 3; 3 folders)
Series 8: Scrapbooks, 1942-2003 (Box 3; 2 folders)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1937-1971, 2004 (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 10: Artwork, 1933-1949, 1980-2000 (Box 3; 3 folders)
Series 11: Sketchbooks, 1944-2005 (Boxes 3-4; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 12: Photographs, 1930-circa 2004 (Box 4; 0.25 linear feet)
American Federation of Arts; Anuszkiewicz, Richard; Associated American Artists; Audubon Artists (New York, N.Y.); DeCordova and Dana Museum and Park; Dienes, Sari; Herz, Nat, 1920-1964; Kandinsky, Wassily, 1866-1944; Koppelman, Dorothy; Kranz, Sheldon; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Ozenfant, Amédée, 1886-1966; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973; Pond, Clayton, 1941-; Pratt Graphics Center; Print Council of America; Rebay, Hilla, 1890-1967; School of Visual Arts (New York, N.Y.); Siegel, Eli, 1902-; Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation; Stamos, Theodoros, 1922-1997; Terrain Gallery; Art--Study and teaching; Artists' studios; Gallery owners--New York (State)--New York; Illustrated letters; Photographs; Printmakers--New York (State)--New York; Prints--Technique; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; World War, 1939-1945
- Biographical Material, 1940-2001; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Scattered biographical material on Chaim Koppelman and Dorothy Koppelman includes: resumes, an artist's statement, an induction order by the United States Army, and entries in Who Is Who directories. Miscellaneous items consist of a receipt documenting Chaim Koppleman's attendance at the Municipal Art School in Bristol, England and Dorothy Koppleman's transcript of grades from Brooklyn College. Interspersed among the files are letters and clippings.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by subject and thereafter in chronological order.
  - Chaim Koppelman (Box 1)
    - Resumes, circa 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - United States Induction Order, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Entry in Print World Directory, 1985-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dorothy Koppelman (Box 1)
    - Resumes, circa 1963-circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Award from Brooklyn Society of Artists, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Entries in Who's Who Directories, 1975; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1942-2003; Series 2; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains personal and general correspondence.
  Personal correspondence includes holiday and greeting cards, postcards, telegrams, an address book, artwork, scattered receipts, clippings, exhibition announcements and photographs. Also found are many ilustrated letters and sketches by Chaim Koppelman and others.
  Much of personal correspondence consists of love letters between Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman. Also found is Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman's correspondence with family and friends. Chaim's letters to Dorothy and others provide a detailed view of his life in the army and include references to his art studies at Art College in Western England and at the L'Ecole des Beaux Arts in France and to the paintings and sculptures that he has completed. There are letters from Eli Siegel to Chaim Koppelman.
  General correspondence contains mostly incoming letters to Chaim Koppelman from collectors, students, colleagues, and various arts institutions. Letters relate to exhibitions, sales of artwork, course assignments, requests for biographical information and recommendations. Attachments to letters include curriculum vitae, exhibition schedules, invoices, receipts, a loan agreement, and clippings. There are some letters from Dorothy Koppelman and Adja Yunkers.
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman Correspondence, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9-18)
    - Eli Siegel Letters to Chaim Koppelman, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Chaim Koppelman Correspondence, 1950-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
    - Loose Envelopes, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1971-2003 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    - Loose Envelopes, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings and Notes, 2005; 1930s-1989; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes annotated typescripts and handwritten drafts of writings and notes. Many of the writings by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman were prepared for talks at the Terrain Gallery, Laurel Gallery, and other venues. Interspersed among the writings are artist's statements and scattered printed material. A file of poems by Chaim Koppelman includes his letters to Eli Siegel; many of the letters are illustrated.
  Writings by others consists of a few poems by Louis Dienes.
  Writings and notes are arranged by subject and filed within folders in chronological order.
  - By Chaim Koppelman (Box 1)
    - On Various Artists, 1949-circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Gallery Talks and Discussions, 1949,1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "A Twentieth Century Direction for Art and Criticism,", circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "Why Aesthetic Realism Matters As to Art,", 1959; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Artist's Statements, 1951-circa 1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "On Art and the Family,", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - On Printmaking, circa 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Relevance of the Siegel Theory of Opposites to the Work of Roy Lichtenstein, Clayton Pond, and Richard Anuszkiewicz, 1968; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "This is the Way I See Aesthetic Realism,", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Napolean Accompanied,", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Poems by Chaim Koppelman and Eli Siegel, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - By Dorothy Koppelman (Box 1)
    - Various Essays on Art, circa 1950s-1961 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Artist's Statements, 1930s-1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - By Others, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
- Subject Files, 1942-2004; Series 4; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Subject files reflect Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman's projects, memberships,and professional interests. Files contain correspondence, biographical information, receipts, annotated checklists, price lists, entry forms, press releases, printed material, clippings, brochures, catalogs, photographs, and slides.
  - American Society of Contemporary Artists - Dorothy Koppelman, 1993-2003 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Anchorage, Alaska, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Art Correspondence, 1980s-1987 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Art for Peace, 1969; 1965 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Artist's Frame Shop Gallery, 1972-2002 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Associated American Artists - Chaim Koppelman, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Atelier 17 - Chaim Koppelman, 1954-1955; 1990 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Audubon Society, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Binghamton Print International, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Robert Blackburn Workshop, 1950s-2000 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Brooklyn Museum Gift - Chaim Koppelman, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Brooklyn Museum - New Prints, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - 498 Broome Street Studio, New York, NY, 1963-2000 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Broome Street Graphics Workshop, 1958-1975 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Comments on Chaim Koppelman's Work, 1950s-2000 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Creative Artists Program Service, Inc., 1966; 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Guggenheim Fellowships - Chaim Koppelman, 1958-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Guggenheim Gift - Chaim Koppelman, 1942; 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Graphic Society, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chaim Koppelman - Awards and Collections, 1954-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chaim Koppelman - Collections, 1966-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dorothy Koppelman's Articles, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Museum Acquisitions, 1956-1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Academy of Design, 1977-2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Academy of Design - Edvard Munch, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ozenfant School of the Fine Arts, 1977; 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Picasso Article by Chaim Koppelman, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Picasso's Man With a Lamb, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Print Club, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - School of Visual Arts, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Society of American Graphic Artists, circa 1950s-2004; undated (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Studio 82, 82 West 3rd Street, New York, NY, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Tiffany Foundation Award, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Underground, Correspondence and Reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - United States Information Agency, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Veterans' Artists' League, 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Weyhe Gallery, 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Teaching Files, 1940s-2006; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  Teaching files of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman include: biographical information, letters, memoranda, syllabi, course outlines, lesson plans, teaching notes, drafts of lectures, student papers, class assignments, a supervision report, a contract, printed material, and photographs. Among the printed materials are clippings, brochures for classes and lectures, announcements, invitations, and exhibition catalogs. A notebook contains Chaim Koppelman's teaching notes and lectures for his art education classes at New York University; interspersed among the pages are sketches.
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order and thereafter in chronological order.
  - Arts for Classes for Children - Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman, 2006; 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Art of Drawing as Art, 1985-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Brooklyn College, 1948-1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Brooklyn College - Dorothy Koppelman Art Class, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - National Academy of Art School, 1983-1999 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - New York University - Chaim Koppelman, 1947-1975 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Other Schools - Chaim Koppelman, 1946-1951; 1970s (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rhodes School - Chaim Koppelman, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - School of Visual Arts, 2005; 1940s-1996 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
  - State University Teachers College at New Paltz, 1952-1958 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Exhibition Files, 1940s-2005; Series 6; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  This series documents solo and group exhibitions of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman. Files include biographical material, correspondence, price lists, sales of artwork, loan agreements, a contract, receipts, printed material, and photographs. Materials represent Chaim Koppelman's professional affiliations with American Federation of Arts, Associated American Artists, Pratt Center for Contemporary Printmaking, and Print Council of America. Included are photographs of Chaim Koppelman, Marthe Ozenfant, and others at an exhibition opening; also included are photographs of artwork.
  Exhibition materials can also be found in Series 2: Correspondence, Series 4: Subject Files, Series 8: Scrapbooks, and Series 12: Photographs.
  Files were kept in the order that they were maintained by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman. Materials are arranged by subject and thereafter filed in chronological order.
  - Chaim Koppelman Exhibitions, 1949-2000 (Box 2, Folder 38-42)
  - Chaim Koppelman Exhibition Correspondence, 1950-1967 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Chaim Koppelman - Price Lists, 1940s-1966; undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Dorothy Koppelman Exhibitions, 1950s-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Dorothy Koppelman Exhibitions - Photographs of Artwork, 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman Exhibitions, 1956-2005 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
- Personal Business Records, 1944-1969; Series 7; 3 Folders Box 3
  This series houses scattered business records mostly relating to the Terrain Gallery. Included is a copy of an agreement between the founding members of the Terrain Gallery to form a domestic corporation for the purpose of purchasing a five-floor building at 20 West 16th Street, New York, for use as a home and exhibition space.
  Materials include: correspondence, a lease, typescripts and handwritten reports of expenses, receipts, clippings, and a photograph of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman at the 20 West 16th Street building.
  Personal Business Records are arranged by subject and filed within folders in chronological order.
  - Incorporation of Terrain Realty Group, 20 West 16th Street, New York, NY, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Financial Documents re 20 West 16th Street and 39 Grove Street, New York, NY, 1954-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Martha Beard - Lease for Apartment at 355 East 72nd Street, New York, NY, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Scrapbooks, 1942-2003; Series 8; 2 Folders Box 3
  Two scrapbooks provide a partial overview of the Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman exhibition history. Scrapbooks contain a variety of documentation: biographical information, artist's statements, press releases, awards, printed material, and photographs of artwork. Printed material includes clippings of exhibition announcements, articles, and reviews; also found are some rare exhibition catalogs.
  The scrapbooks were dismantled.
  Scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  - Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman Exhibition Scrapbook (Dismantled), 1942-2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Dorothy Koppelman Exhibition Scrapbook (Dismantled), 1961-2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Printed Material, 2004; 1937-1971; Series 9; 0.25 Linear feet Box 3
  Printed material includes newspaper clippings and art magazines from Chaim Koppelman's high school, and a few newsletters distributed by the United States Army Corps. An issue of the high school art magazine includes Chaim Koppelman's article on WPA art. A reproduction of a woodcut and sketch drawn by Koppelman in his teens is also included.
  Among the miscellaneous items are: a reproduction of a book plate designed by Chaim Koppelman, an article on Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman and the Terrain Gallery members, and an Artist's Proof featuring Chaim and Dorothy's work.